<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>joey.in_progress</title>
    <description>a work in progress: join me on my journey into programming</description>
    <link>http://axhi.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://axhi.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 15:29:35 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 15:29:35 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Let the job hunt...begin</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Last week Monday I began the journey into finding a job. I’ve been here before, my cohortmates have all been here before, but this time it feels a little different. I think the difference, for me at least, tends to be that my qualifications seem to better fit the jobs I am applying for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t to say that I think I am ultra-qualified for everythign I’m applying to, but I do feel better than when I graduated undergrad with a B.S. in Communications and was qualified for just about nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;the-search&quot;&gt;The Search&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have spent most of my time looking for companies that I find inspiring and seem like genuine places I would like to work. This is quite the shift from just blindly applying to anythign and everything that shows up on a job board (which is where I was 3 years ago).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve narrowed it down to about 20 or so companies that I’m putting my effort into. This means reaching out with cold emails, finding similarities with employees and showing my genuine interest in working for their company.  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;my-free-time&quot;&gt;My Free Time&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the job hunt is serious business, I do intend to use my free time wisely. I have watched almost 2 seasons of Glee &amp;lt;– Time well spent. And then I’ve been working on my Scheduling app. The app is keeping my code game strong while Glee is a constant reminder that I cannot sing, but will one day learn how!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to try my hardest to post more often as I have the free time now and should be contributing. &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Sep 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/jobs/glee/2014/09/23/job-hunt/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/jobs/glee/2014/09/23/job-hunt/</guid>
        
        
        <category>jobs</category>
        
        <category>glee</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Phase 1 assessments in the bag</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Woah, what a three week period. DBC has proved every bit exciting as I thought it would be. I have felt happy, angry, sad, excited, challenged, comforted, loved and basically any other emotion over the past 3 weeks. Today we were assessed on our understanding of the Phase 1 fundamentals and if the instructor’s felt we were ready to move onto the next part of the program. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think a lot of people are extremely scared of this because they see it as a pass/fail type situation. The truth of the matter is, this place exists to make the individual the best possible entry level development candidate they can be. DBC is clearly a business, but they are truly here to make sure you get your value out of the program. If someone has gone through 3 weeks and isn’t really ready to move on, that person shouldn’t really want to move on…to be honest. You aren’t here to get a ‘grade’ or a diploma, you are here to try and level yourself with the playing field. You are going up against CS grads that can put that exceptional line on their resume.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Someone from Phase 2 said today, “If I have not learned everything they taught me in this phase, I don’t want to move on to the next one.” It is, in a nutshell, as simple as that. For any incoming boots or prospective boots-please remember this. Not moving on is not easy. You are left behind as all your new-found friends are moving on. There are probably many emotions aside from that running through your mind as well; “That’s another 3 weeks without pay.”, “I have a family, they need me.” and many other thoughts. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was fortunate enough to get a firm grasp on all the materials presented to me in Phase 1, but am seeing a few of my cohortmates repeating. I just want them to know that no one thinks they are inadequate and your Bobolink family will always be here for any help/advice. In the end, we all came here for the same intentions and will leave here at the same level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Tweet Tweet”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 31 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/dbc,/assesment/2014/07/31/phase1-assessments/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/dbc,/assesment/2014/07/31/phase1-assessments/</guid>
        
        
        <category>dbc,</category>
        
        <category>assesment</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ruby Strings, the difference between &#39; and &#39;&#39;</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we worked in SQL queries and writing Ruby to translate SQL database rows into Ruby objects. This, in itself, was just extremely exciting and warrants its own blog post, but today I want to write about the difference between using single and double quotes in Ruby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in the world of an actual &lt;code&gt;String&lt;/code&gt;, Ruby does not necessarily care. If we have two strings:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;string one&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str2&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;string two&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; &amp;quot;string one&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;p&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;str2&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; &amp;quot;string two&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both &lt;code&gt;str1&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;str2&lt;/code&gt; returned a string of the same format, no difference can be noticed. So, in this regard, using a single/double quote is solely preference. Some programmers feel the necessity to keep the code “clean” so they use single quotes, and others like the literal translation as in &lt;code&gt;this variable is a string&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the real fun begins when we look into interpolation and Ruby methods. If we were to try to send a command to a SQL database that looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;vg&quot;&gt;$db_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;SELECT * FROM db_name WHERE id = &lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;#{&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;si&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; id in this case would be 1&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;vg&quot;&gt;$db_name&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;execute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;SELECT * FROM db_name WHERE id = #{id}&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; id in this case would translate to \#{id}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see from these two examples, using a single quotes would escape the &lt;code&gt;id&lt;/code&gt;, not allowing us to search for the specific value. And since SQL requires you to send its statement as a string that is basically inputs into a terminal like command, you need to pass some form of string. You may be saying to yourself, “Joey, why don’t you just use the literal variable then?” Well, if we did that it would just pass a string id as the lookup value so we would still be in the same situation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may be cleaner to use single quotes for most situations, be very careful when you are needing to do some interpolation as the value will not translate to what you are looking for. Anyway, that is some basic Ruby string and single vs. double quote situations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/ruby,/strings/2014/07/29/ruby-strings/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/ruby,/strings/2014/07/29/ruby-strings/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ruby,</category>
        
        <category>strings</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>New site backbone</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As you may have noticed, this little website of mine has a little bit of a new layout. The main changes I made were to use a Jekyll backbone to run my posts and website. I’m still hosting on Github (as is evident by the url) but I want everyone to stick with me while I work on making this site awesome!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/website/changes/2014/07/27/jekyll-switch/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/website/changes/2014/07/27/jekyll-switch/</guid>
        
        
        <category>website</category>
        
        <category>changes</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Two weeks down, seven to go...</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/solong.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;My helpful screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been far too long since my last post and it isn’t because I’ve been crazy busy…which I have been, but more that my exhaustion level after a day at DBC is so high that I just want to unwind at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This week consisted of a mock-assessment to properly analyze our status with the material at this point and mine went pretty well. The days are packed with excitement, frustration, enlightenment, fear and possibly all ranges of emotions you could think of. We have lectures, emotional empathy training, stand-ups, pairing sessions, assessments, code reviews and many other new things every day. My time has been so fulfilling thus far and I am extremely eager to get up every morning and start a new day at DBC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Chicago life has been pretty awesome thus far as well. I have had Portillo’s like 4 times and have no plans on slowing down. I wish I had more time to see more of the city and go out and about but my addiction to learning doesn’t allow me much escape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m now realizing this blog post is jumping all over the place, and I apologize for that. I, in conclusion, wanted to write a little about things I’ve learned thus far. Some key points are object oriented design, data parsing and command line arguments. It is a little odd to realize we are spending so much time in the command line when in just 1 short week, we will jump heavily into the web but the building blocks are essential. The programs I’m writing now are so much more sophisticated and complex than anything I’ve done to before today and could not be happier about it. I’ll look at a snippet of my code for parsing CSV data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;def&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;return&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@list&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;CSV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;foreach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;todo.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
        &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;c1&quot;&gt;#=&amp;gt; adds each item to the list array.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two weeks ago, I wouldn’t have exactly known what was going on on the above code and I’ll try and explain as best I can here. First I am using the &lt;code&gt;CSV&lt;/code&gt; class for Ruby so I will need to require it at the top of my document. Then, I have a method called read_file that takes no parameters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next line is basically a little “only run this method one time” check. It will return the list of a list exists. It is a little check trick I learned here at DBC. &lt;code&gt;@list&lt;/code&gt; is a class variable as can be denoted by the &lt;code&gt;@&lt;/code&gt; symbol. You don’t know it from this snippet but I have initialized this class with &lt;code&gt;@list = nil&lt;/code&gt;. That is our way of making the return line work. The first check is saying &lt;code&gt;return @list&lt;/code&gt; if it exists, and since we set it to nil, it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;CSV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;foreach&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;todo.csv&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;do&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;vi&quot;&gt;@list&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Task&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;item&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line is where all the magic happens. To learn a bit more about the Ruby CSV class, click &lt;a href=&quot;http://ruby-doc.org/stdlib-1.9.2/libdoc/csv/rdoc/CSV.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. So this is calling the CSV class and running a foreach on it by passing the parameter of a filename to it. The do &lt;code&gt;|item|&lt;/code&gt; snippet is a way of running the method iteratively and return the block of code for each line that .foreach returns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The method takes a CSV file, parses each line, and returns the line into a new Task object. I didn’t do the best job explaining this, I can tell, but it makes total sense to me. I’m excited that I’m learning-and learning so fast.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/dbc/phase-1/2014/07/25/two-weeks-down/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/dbc/phase-1/2014/07/25/two-weeks-down/</guid>
        
        
        <category>dbc</category>
        
        <category>phase-1</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Ask away</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The art of asking a ‘good question’ is quickly becoming a very important aspect of my coding thus far. I often find myself searching the Internet for an answer to a puzzling question re our DBC prep work thus far. It would be easy to search the question in its entirety but that would just give you results that tell you the entire answer and not how to get there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have asked countless questions in my life thus far and can only imagine that number will continuously grow. I haven’t really written down a lot of questions so I went to stackoverflow to seek out a question to review and here is what I found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Ruby&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Basic&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;authentication&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;I&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;want&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;build&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;an&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;application&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;that&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;will&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;be&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;making&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;a&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;request&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;to&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;twitter&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;search&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;api&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;basic&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;authentication&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;method&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;In&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;searches&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;I&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;came&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;across&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;this&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;following&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;piece&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;of&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;code&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;using&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;rest&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;client&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;package&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;resource&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;RestClient&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Resource&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;http://example.com&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; 
&lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:user&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;user&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;ss&quot;&gt;:password&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;password&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;however&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;it&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;returned&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;bad request: 400&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Can&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;anyone&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;advise?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, I think the title doesn’t at all build into what the question is, and is a little misleading. That is an immediate turn off from this question to anyone that may be of help with authentication or vice versa. The question, itself is detailed and provides a lot of helpful insight for people looking to answer it. The asker is specific and really delves into what they are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The big issue with this question is that they don’t provide any output for their error here so the first poster found that and asked a new question in response. If the output posts here and the user community is able to post an answer, the asker would have been better positioned had they responded with that initially.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 13 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/cultural/dbc/2014/07/13/ask-away/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/cultural/dbc/2014/07/13/ask-away/</guid>
        
        
        <category>cultural</category>
        
        <category>dbc</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Active Record</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Wo-hoo! Active record! While one would not regularly address something such as Active Record with such excitement and enthusiasm, it is extremely important to the Model-View-Controller (MVC) model which Ruby relies on. Active record handles the transformation of data from a database, such as a SQL table, to a Ruby object.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The great thing about Active Record is that you can bypass SQL statements and queries by just using ActiveRecord to map the database row and perform the function for you. And then you can create models to represent table rows and headings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, we can go through a table for a user profile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Users&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;ActiveRecord&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Base&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;end&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This assigns the Users class to the table of the same name. Now, however the table was created, we can call methods from the class, after creating a new one based on our table schema.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sql&quot; data-lang=&quot;sql&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;CREATE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;TABLE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;users&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;id&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;NOT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;NULL&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;auto_increment&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;username&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;varchar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;varchar&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;mi&quot;&gt;255&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;),&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;age&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;int&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From that SQL table we can now call all these elements after making a new class from our ActiveRecord class above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-ruby&quot; data-lang=&quot;ruby&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;user1&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;no&quot;&gt;Users&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;new&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;user1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;name&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;John Smith&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;user1&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;email&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;jsmith@jsmith.com&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;user1.age = 25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now when we call these elements, they will populate from the database we setup. Following the CRUD method, which is Create, Read, Update, Delete - modifications can be made the table and actions cal be called as it is stored in an array type object that can be iterated and what have you.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 06 Jul 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/dbc/phase-0/active-record/2014/07/06/active-record/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/dbc/phase-0/active-record/2014/07/06/active-record/</guid>
        
        
        <category>dbc</category>
        
        <category>phase-0</category>
        
        <category>active-record</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hooray for optimization!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;SQL databases are an amazing tool and can do a ridiculous amount of things. The problem with amazing tools like this one is that can perform so many functions, which creates a whole slew of computer processing problems. So, as we learn about databases and how to create, manipulate, and store data we will also need to learn how to optimize these tables to return query results in the shortest amount of time possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After performing some research on the subject I found a few things to do to insure a timely database query. The first thing to keep in mind is to fully understand how your database will be used. The queries you will run on your database, how often, and how complex can be controlled if you know what you are looking for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a link to a Microsoft checklist that is useful for increasing SQL service performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;scale-up-vs-scale-out&quot;&gt;Scale Up vs Scale Out&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scaling is the process of literally adding more computing power to your servers. Scaling up is considered vertical scaling, this is done by adding more processors and RAM to a server (beefing up the one you have). Scaling out is considered horizontal, and that is adding more physical servers. They each have their pros/cons but as far as things we can accomplish in our code, it doesn’t relate that much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/optimize.png&quot; alt=&quot;Optimzation image&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;schemaqueries&quot;&gt;Schema/Queries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The schema of a database should contain appropriate data types and all primary keys should be properly defined. It is important to not fill a database with keys that aren’t necessary or that can be utilized elsewhere. As far as Queries go, there are a lot of things that can be done to speed up results and query times. A few that should become part of our regular code should be to only return rows/columns that are needed. Try not to run &lt;code&gt;*&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;SELECT&lt;/code&gt; unless you need to return all fields. Also, operators such as &lt;code&gt;NOT LIKE&lt;/code&gt;, query long and can be written with well formed &lt;code&gt;IN&lt;/code&gt; statements instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are so many ways to just shorten queries and query loads that optimizing the database itself hasn’t even come up yet. A lot of my research said that optimizing database performance will start with good database design. This can be accomplished by keeping in mind the Schema/Query section I listed and going through the handy checklist from the resources section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://msdn.microsoft.com/en-us/library/ff647681.aspx&quot;&gt;Microsoft’s SQL Checklist&lt;/a&gt; » 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.foliotek.com/devblog/sql-server-database-optimization-a-beginners-guide/&quot;&gt;Foliotek’s Optimization Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2014 07:05:10 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://axhi.github.io/ruby,/optimization/2014/06/24/hooray-for-optimization/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://axhi.github.io/ruby,/optimization/2014/06/24/hooray-for-optimization/</guid>
        
        
        <category>ruby,</category>
        
        <category>optimization</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
